[ Music ]
>> There were lots of campus Ethernet's
because they were really easy to deploy
and you could put them in a department
and then you could run a wire between two departments
and you had a bigger network and so we've grown up networks sort
of by agglomeration in lots of different university campuses
and NSF came up with some money, said, oh, we've got a little bit
in our budget where we could get some 56 kilobit lines
and tie those campuses together and they did that,
made the NSF met phase one.
But now you're tying together 10 megabit campus infrastructure
with 56 kilobit wires and it was wildly popular because people
that couldn't talk could suddenly talk
and they're sending emails and moving huge files
and everybody's really excited about this technology.
But any one of those campuses could oversubscribe the net
by a factor of a thousand.
So we had a lot of packets piling up and getting dropped.
At the time I was a researcher at Lawrence Berkeley Lab,
which is in the hills up above the Berkeley campus
and I was also teaching on the Berkeley campus.
Even back in those days, which was mid '80s, we had a,
for every class there was a messages group, you know,
like a little news group that was set up.
All the assignments would be put online and I was trying
to get course materials from my office in LBL down to a machine
in Evans Hall at Berkeley and there was like zero throughput
in the net, it was one packet every 10 minutes or so
and it seemed unbelievably bad and I went down and talked
to Mike Carroll who was heading the BSD group,
the people that developed Berkeley Unix
and he's getting reports of these problems from all
over the country from, in those days,
the easiest way to start running TCP/IP was to bring
up Berkeley Unix because there was a ARPA funded very nice
implementation in it and everybody was seeing poor
performance so we talked for a long time that day
and on succeeding days about, well, what's going wrong,
is there some mistake in the protocol implementation,
is there some mistake in the protocol,
this thing was working on smaller scale tests
and then it suddenly fell apart.
I think we struggled for three or four months just going
through the code, writing tools to capture packet traces
and looking at the packet traces and trying
to sort out what was breaking and I remember the two
of us were sitting in Mike's office after we'd been pounding
our head against the wall for literally months and one
of us, I can't remember which one, said, "You know,
the reason I can't figure out why it's breaking is
I don't understand how it ever worked."
You know, we're sending these bits out at 10 megabits,
they're zipping across campus, they're running
into this 56 kilobit wire, we expect them to go
through that wire, pop out on the other side, go through.
How could that function?
That turned out to be the crucial starting point.
At that point, we started saying, "Well, what is there
about this protocol that makes it work?
How does it deal with all of those bandwidth changes?
How does it deal with the multiple hops?"
So this picture, that direction is time,
this direction is bandwidth.
So that's a fat pipe and that's a skinny pipe.
And the scale of the time is, you know,
this is a 10 megabit pipe and this is a 56 kilobit pipe.
So here the difference is about 3 to 1,
it was really closer to 100 to 1.
And time, seconds times bits per second equals bits.
So each of these little boxes in there is a packet,
it's the number of bits in a packet.
And if you scrunch it down in bandwidth, it's got to spread
out in time because the number of bits doesn't change.
And so see the burst of packets,
the window's worth of packets gets launched, it's going to fly
through the net until it hits this fast to slow transition.
And then because the packets have to stretch out in time,
they all have to sit there and wait as they're fed
into the slower wire.
And you, they pop out the other side, they get spread
out by this bottleneck, by this slower wire.
Once they're spread out, they stay spread out, right?
There's nothing to push them back together again.
They hit a receiver, it turns every data packet into an ACK.
So you've got a bunch of ACKs
that are going back towards the sender
and they remember what's the right spacing
for that bottleneck.
So the ACKs get back to the sender
and every ACK gets turned into a data packet.
So we can see the data packets flowing back.
And this is after one round trip time.
Now the packets are coming out perfectly spaced so they go by,
a new one goes into the net in exactly the time it takes a
packet to exit from the bottleneck.
So these ACKs are sort of acting as a clock
that tells you, tells the sender when it's safe
to inject every new packet.
And they're always going to be spaced
by whatever is the slowest point in the net.
>> And the key thing is, is how do you, how quick,
how can you get the steady state sort
of most quickly without wasting?
>> Yeah. And the issue, the failure we saw was,
this works perfectly after you've exchanged a round trip
time worth of packets.
But when you're starting up, when you're here,
there's no clock.
And so the hard part on TCP is not getting it running,
it's getting it started because once you've got it running,
you've got a clock that tells you exactly what to do.
So if you turn them on, suddenly you get
in this repetitive failure mode
where you saturate the buffering that was available
at some gateway and then when you retransmit,
you do the same thing again.
So you're always losing packets.
But if you turned it on more gradually,
then you wouldn't overload the buffering and you'd get enough
of a clock going so that you control the amount
of backlog to fit the available buffer
but you'd still be growing the number of packets in flight
so that you'd eventually get a, you'd start with a kind
of sporadic clock but you'd eventually fill in the details
and get a per packet clock.
>> How did you get it to the point where it was
in all the TCP/IP implementations on the planet?
Because they kind of have to cooperate in a way.
>> So remember it was a much simpler time when you're talking
about all the TCP/IP implementations on the planet.
At that time there were like four.
So there was the Berkeley Unix one.
There was the MIT PCTCP.
There was a BBN one that was used in butterflies and imps
and there was a Multics one.
I took the couple of TCP kernel modules that we'd been working
on, packaged them up in a tar.
I had this horrible driver hack that would let us snarf packets
from the kernel, I mean it was really a horrible driver hack.
It was the way you said what you wanted to snarf was by ADB
in the kernel you wrote in binary some new values.
These are the ports that I want to look at
and the driver would capture those into a circular buffer
and you'd read kernel memory to pull that buffer out.
Craig Laris and Chris Torak who were working in my group
at LBL and were both long-time kernel hackers were just
embarrassed at this and they put together a really nice clean
driver thing called BPF, the Berkeley Packet Filter
that would let you pull packets out of the kernel
by a very efficient I/O control interface.
And so we bundled all of that up and on the TCP/IP mailing list
which in those days was, TCP/IP was very experimental,
it was very leading edge and pretty much everybody
who was playing with it was on that mailing list
to announce that this stuff was available.
A bunch of people FTPed it, tried it, it blew up,
sent kernel core dumps and bug reports
and fixed the bug reports and put new versions out.
Somebody would immediately come back and say, panicked here,
do you want the K-Core?
And they'd go, oh no, embarrassed, put out a new version,
go out, somebody else would come back and say panicked here
and fix that and just cycled like that and after about a day
we got a version that didn't immediately panic
and then started working on the actual algorithms
and a little bit of tuning to make sure
that it actually did good all the time and didn't do any harm.
Just completely a community effort
and sort of when the community was saying,
this mostly does good and never seems to do harm,
that's pretty much what Mike needed to put it into the kernel
so he took the community-developed modules
and rolled them into the BSD release.